Guide to the Joel A. Tarr Papers, 1957-1995 AIS.1999.15
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Joel A. Tarr Papers
1957-1995
1980-1981
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Tarr, Joel A. (Joel Arthur)
AIS.1999.15
1.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
The Joel A. Tarr Papers document the Pittsburgh urban development research of Dr. Tarr, a Carnegie Mellon professor of history and public policy, primarily during the 1980s for his publication co-authored with Shelby Stewman, a Carnegie Mellon professor of sociology and demography, "Four Decades of Public-Private Partnerships in Pittsburgh," published in Public-Private Partnerships in American Cities, edited by R. Scott Fosler and Renee Berger in 1982.
Scope and Content Notes
The Joel A. Tarr Papers include materials related to Tarr's research on urban development, specifically for his paper "Four Decades of Public-Private Partnerships in Pittsburgh," published in 1982 (co-authored with Shelby Stewman). This scholarly publication analyzes the differences in public-private partnerships during the periods of the Renaissance I (1945-1969), the Interlude (1970-1977) and Renaissance II (1978-1980) to better understand "present-day Pittsburgh" based on "two sets of interviews conducted with public officials (past and present), chief executive officers of major corporations, and administrative officials and staff of various private voluntary organizations." The first set of interviews (78 total) used for the study are part of the Pittsburgh Renaissance Project: The Stanton Belfour Oral History Collection, 1971-1973 (see Related Material). The second set of interviews was created by Tarr, Shelby Stewman, and Steven Block in 1981. Transcriptions of the 1981 interviews make up Series II of this collection.
Series I of the collection include publications by Tarr and others, case studies and reports, committee proceedings, newspaper clippings, correspondence and research notes, and other materials related to his research between 1957-1995. Series II contains transcripts and notes from oral history interviews conducted by Joel A. Tarr, Shelby Stewman, and Steven Block for the article, "Four Decades of Public-Private Partnerships in Pittsburgh."
Related Material
ACTION Housing, Inc. Records, AIS.2001.11, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Allegheny Conference on Community Development Collection, 1944-1993, AIS.1973.04, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
David Leo Lawrence Papers, 1959-1966, AIS.1978.15, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Michael P. Weber Papers, 1963-1984, AIS.1988.15, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Peter F. Flaherty Papers, 1964-1995, AIS.1999.19, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Pittsburgh, Pa. City Planning Commission Records, 1928-1962, AIS.1976.17, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Pittsburgh Renaissance Project: The Stanton Belfour Oral History Collection, 1971-1973, AIS.1973.24, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Smoke Control Lantern Slide Collection, ca. 1940-1950, AIS.1978.22, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
Series I. Research Files
Series II. Oral Histories
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dr. Joel A. Tarr in 1999.
Previous Citation
Joel A. Tarr Papers, 1957-1995, AIS.1999.15, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Biography
Joel A. Tarr graduated with his B.A. and M.A. in History from Rutgers University in 1956 and 1957, respectively, and graduated with his Ph.D. in History from Northwestern University in 1963. He began teaching at Carnegie Mellon University in 1967. He currently holds joint appointments in the H. John Heinz III School of Public Policy and Management and the Department of Engineering and Public Policy at Carnegie Mellon University. He has published extensively on urban history, the development of urban technological systems, and the history of the urban environment and has received many awards for teaching and research. This collection includes research materials related to his publication, "Four Decades of Public-Private Partnerships in Pittsburgh," published in Public-Private Partnerships in American Cities by R. Scott Fosler and Renee Berger in 1982. Other notable publications include Devastation and Renewal: an Environmental History of Pittsburgh and its Region and The Search for the Ultimate Sink: Urban Pollution in Historical Perspective.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
City planning -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Urban renewal -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Industries -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Politics; Pollution -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Faculty papers; Housing -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Transportation; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Business and Industry; Oral histories (Document genres); Allegheny Conference on Community Development (Pa.); Carnegie-Mellon University -- Faculty; Tarr, Joel A. (Joel Arthur)
- Research Files, 1957-1995; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The Research Files series contains publications, case studies and reports, committee proceedings, newspaper clippings, correspondence and research notes related to Tarr's article, "Four Decades of Public-Private Partnerships in Pittsburgh" published in 1982.
  - "Four Decades of Public-Private Partnership in Pittsburgh" by Shelby Stewman and Joel A. Tarr, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Lawrenceville as a Sustainable Community", February 10, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Comprehensive Housing Strategies: Pittsburgh" (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Committee for Economic Development, Subcommittee on Revitalizing America's Cities, September 24, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Summaries of Case Example Responses from Trustee Companies (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Renaissance II: The Present Prospect and the Continuing Challenge" by James H. Higgins, November 3, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Report on the Convention Center Hotel Review Committee, October 29, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "A Downtown Development Strategy: A Progress Report", August 20, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "The Changing Metropolitan Economy of the 1980s: Public and Private Opportunities" by James H. Higgins, September 23, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Evaluation of the Community Economic Development Demonstration Program", January 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Planning and Urban Design Criteria for the Grant Street East Development, July 27, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1957-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and Notes, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Research for Interviews, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Oral Histories, 1981; II.
  The Oral Histories series includes 24 oral history transcripts and notes by Joel A. Tarr, Shelby Stewman, and Steven Block in 1981 for research related to "Four Decades of Public-Private Partnerships in Pittsburgh" published in 1982.
  - Index to Interviews by the Center for Economic Developement (CED), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Al Bittcher (Vice President and Manager of Mellon Bank's Mellon Square Office), May 6, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Paul Brophy (Director of Department of Housing, Pittsburgh), February 18, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fletcher Byrom (CEO of Koppers), April 10, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Richard Calaguiri (Mayor of Pittsburgh 1977-1988), May 26, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bruce Campbell (Former Executive Secretary to Mayor of Pittsburgh), May 6, 1981 and August 4, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Edward J. Cooke (Allegheny County Democratic Politician), March 20, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - James V. Cunningham (Political Organizer and University of Pittsburgh Professor of Social Work), March 9, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Edward DeLuca (Director of City Development Department of Pittsburgh), January 16, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bob Dickey III (CEO of Dravo Corporation), April 30, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ben Fischer (Professor of Labor Studies and Public Policy and Director of CIO and ACTION-Housing, Pittsburgh), March 18 & 23, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Pete Flaherty (Mayor of Pittsburgh 1969-1977), May 1 & 19, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Steve George (Executive Director of the Urban Redevelopment Authority of Pittsburgh), February 13 & 27, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - H.J. Heinz II (Chairman of H.J. Heinz Company), February 10, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - James Higgins (CEO of Mellon Bank, Retired), April 24, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Henry Hillman (Chairman of Hillman Company), April 29, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Justin Horan (President of Pittsburgh Chamber of Commerce), April 21, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Robert Lurcott (Director of City Planning Department, Pittsburgh), February 27 & March 3, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - David Matter (Executive Secretary to the Mayor of Pittsburgh), May 26, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Jerry McAfee (CEO of Gulf Corporation), April 23, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Abby Mendolson (Urban Redevelopment Authority), January 22, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - John Olson (Senior Vice President at Mellon Bank), May 6, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Robert Pease (Executive Director of the Allegheny Conference on Community Development), February 4, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Jack (John) Robin (Former Executive Secretary to Mayor David Lawrence and Chairman of the Board of URA), February 23, March 2 & 19, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - L. Stanton Williams (CEO of PPG Industries), April 23, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 39)